Finding Aid for Evaluation and Examinations Division (University of Michigan) records, 1927-1971
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Evaluation and Examinations Division (University of Michigan) records 1927-1971
University of Michigan. Evaluation and Examinations Division.
4 linear feet
2012085 Bimu 2
The Division of Evaluation and Examinations was a testing and research unit which oversaw the testing and evaluation of incoming and current University of Michigan students and was tasked with administering several national testing programs to communities throughout the state. The Division was created by the Regents in 1945 as an incorporation of the Bureau of University Research (1927) and the Psychological Clinic (1938). Records include tests and evaluations, data tables, project reports and publications, testing manuals, and correspondence related to the implementation and evaluation of student testing from 1927 to 1971.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received in 2011 (donor number 7926 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The Evaluation and Examinations Division records are open for research except for certain client records restricted by statute or university policy.
The RECORD GROUP record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Patient/Client Records -- Boxes 1
The Evaluations and Examination Division, established in 1945, is the descendant of an earlier service called the Bureau of University Research. In 1927 the Regents created the Bureau of University Research to study the educational activities of the University and provide data for the faculty and administration. The Bureau, under the directorship of Clarence S. Yoakum, began to collect data on students using surveys of background information, psychological evaluations, test scores on entrance exams of various subjects, and subsequent grades earned while studying at the University to incorporate in studies about the predictability of academic success. In 1930 the Bureau became Educational Investigations and was tasked with research to inform educational policies, especially those related to admissions and student placement. This office continued to operate until Yoakum's death in 1945.
The Psychological Clinic then assumed the responsibilities of Educational Investigations. At the time, the Clinic was tasked with providing psychological services to incoming students and was responsible for administering, scoring and reporting results for all psychological and educational tests being used for student admission, course placement, and counseling. In September 1945, Wilma Donahue, administrator of the Psychological Clinic, recommended the establishment of the Bureau of Psychological Services of the Institute for Human Adjustment to manage the testing services needed due to the rapid increase in student enrollment after World War II.
The Bureau of Psychological Services was organized into four autonomous divisions, including the Testing Division and the Research Division, but in 1950 under the directorship of E. Lowell Kelly, the Research Division was dissolved into the other divisions. The Testing Division then became the Evaluation and Examinations Division, and assumed all responsibilities for the testing of incoming and current University students and subsequent evaluation and research to inform University policies. The first Chief of this division was M.W. Travers (1945-1948), followed by Edward Furst (1948-1956), John Milholland (1956-1964) and finally Benno Fricke (1964-1982, served as Assistant Chief 1955-1964).
The functions of the Evaluation and Examination Division (EED) involved student testing, primarily through the Orientation Testing Program for freshmen and transfer students and research for admissions policies and educational research. It provided services to University faculty and staff in creating, administering and evaluating course exams and scoring methods as well as the evaluation of courses and curricula. In addition to collecting and providing data on University student testing, the EED was responsible for the administration of several national testing programs for high school through graduate students (including the College Entrance Examination Board's Scholastic Aptitude Test (SAT) and the Graduate Record Examination (GRE)). Beginning in the 1960s a major function of the EED was the introduction of computer technology for test scoring to the University.
In 1968 the Evaluation and Examination Division was affiliated with the Center for Research on Learning and Teaching (CRLT, established 1962). In 1976 the EED became the Office of Evaluation and Examinations (OEE), which was administered under the CRLT. The director of the CRLT was psychologist Wilbert McKeachie, but the OEE continued to be managed by Benno Fricke until 1982. It continued to function as an office for administering tests, including a new computerized course evaluation system for the CRLT.
In 1998 the OEE separated from the CRLT and became an independent office, the Office of Evaluation and Examinations, reporting to the Associate Provost for Academic Affairs. It continued to function under the directorship of James Kulik as a service for evaluating programs and scoring exams for students, researchers, administrators and instructors at the University.
--------------------
Sources Consulted
The University of Michigan, an Encyclopedic Survey Volume V (The University of Michigan 1940-75, Ferol Brinkman, Editor)
A Statistical Summary of the Records of Students Entering the University of Michigan as Freshmen in the decade 1927-1936 (P.S. Dwyer et al., University of Michigan Administrative Studies Volume 1 Number 4, [1940])
Untitled document listing the functions of EED, in folder Evaluation and Examinations Division, Function of -- 8/6/57, Box 2
Office of Evaluation and Examinations: About E&E - http://www.umich.edu/~eande/about/about.htm (accessed May 2012)
The records of the Evaluation and Examinations Division (EED) span from 1927 to 1971 and include student testing data and statistical summaries, project reports and statistical summaries, correspondence, memoranda, publications, bulletins, agendas, manuals and guidelines related to testing, scoring and evaluating various tests the EED administered. These tests include the ACE College Aptitude Test, the Cooperative Reading Comprehension Test, the Michigan English Proficiency Test, the College Qualification Test, the Michigan Math Placement Test, the Cooperative Chemistry Test, and the Differential Aptitude Test for entering freshmen. The Division was responsible for administering and scoring tests for high schools throughout the state as well as incoming University students, including the Scholastic Aptitude Test (SAT), the Graduate Record Examination (GRE), the Law School Admission Test (LSAT) and the Medical College Admission Test (MCAT). Also contains materials related to the Opinion, Attitude and Interest Survey (OAIS), which was developed and administered by the EED.
The records are arranged into five series: Student Test Data, Project Files, Test Manuals and Guides, Statistical Reports, and Benno Fricke Materials. The individual series are arranged by year except for Project Files, which is generally arranged by project title or year labels, as these were collected from multiple filing cabinets and the original folder order has been lost. In all series except Student Test Data, testing data which contained student names and scores or grades or other secure information has been removed and destroyed.
Subjects:
Fricke, Benno G.; Education--Evaluation.; Educational tests and measurements.; Grades and marking (Students); Prediction of scholastic success.; University of Michigan. Evaluation and Examinations Division.; University of Michigan--Examinations.
- Student Test Data 1927-1936, 1938-1947
  The Student Test Data, 1927-1947 series (1 ft.) consists of bound volumes of test data recorded from Freshman Examinations (1927-1936), later termed Orientation Week Testing (1938-1947). Records are from the Bureau of Educational Research (1927-1930), Office of the Director of Educational Investigations (1930-1945) and the Bureau of Psychological Services (1945-1947). Records in this series are restricted due to the presence of name-identifiable test results. Data and analysis from the tests was published in 1940 in the publication A Statistical Summary of the Records of Students Entering the University of Michigan as Freshmen in the decade 1927-1936 by P.S. Dwyer, Charlotte Horner and C.S. Yoakum (Michigan Administrative Studies Volume 1 Number 4).
  - University of Michigan Freshman Examination Scores 1927-1930 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2030 ]
  - University of Michigan Freshman Examination Scores 1931-1933 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2033 ]
  - University of Michigan Freshman Examination Scores 1934-1936 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2036 ]
  - University of Michigan Orientation Week Testing Program 1938-1941 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2041 ]
  - University of Michigan Orientation Week Testing Program 1941-1943 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2043 ]
  - University of Michigan Orientation Week Testing Program 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2045 ]
  - University of Michigan Orientation Week Testing Program 1945-1947 (Box 1)
    [CR RESTRICTED until July 1, 2047 ]
- Project Files 1947-1964
  The Project Files 1947-1954 series (2.0 ft.) consists of folders and binders related to projects completed by the Evaluation and Examination Division of the Bureau of Psychological Services, including reports, memoranda and correspondence, publications and testing data. This series is not arranged in a set order as these folders were removed from multiple filing cabinets before being transferred and the original order was lost, though they are generally identified by project number and/or project title, or publication title and/or year.
  - Freshman Test Study Correlations of Course Grades and the Freshman Tests 1948 (Box 2)
  - Academic Aptitude Test Graduate Validation Studies 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - ACE -- GPA Memo to Counselors and Advisers 1954 (Box 2)
  - Assessment of the Academic Aptitude of the Graduate Student, Travers and Wallace circa 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Cooperative English Test C2: T Reading Comprehension, A Report on (Speed and Level Versus Rate and Acc.) 1956 (Box 2)
  - DAT (Differential Aptitude Test), Michigan Norms for, 1956-57 (Box 2)
  - Dentistry 133, Questionnaire on January 1956 (Box 2)
  - Engineering -- A cross-validation study of predictive charts for GPA January 27, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Students, Academic Performance of 1954 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Students, Test Performance and Academic Achievement 1952 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation of the Outcomes of Teaching in English circa 1945-1948 (Box 2)
  - Some Notes on the Evaluation and Examinations Division of the Bureau of Psychological Services, ca. 1948-56 (Box 2)
  - Occasional Bulletin of the Evaluation and Examination Division, Bureau of Psychological Services, "Machine-Scoring Services," 1959 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation and Examinations Division Speculations re: 10-Year Growth 1956 (Box 2)
  - Examination Services Provided by the University 1947 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen, Fall SAT scores of students who entered various units of the UM 1955 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen, Fall 1956 ACE Total Score High School Percentile Rank, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen, Average Total ACE Score 1952 through 1956 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen, Predicted First Semester Grade-Point Averages for Non-Resident UM 1957 (Box 2)
  - Comparison of Entering Freshmen in Nine Schools & Colleges, Fall, 1952-1954 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen entering UM, Fall 1952 Number of Students in Actual Sample Enrolled in Given Colleges, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen: Comparison of Freshmen Entering in 1948, 1951 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen: Comparison of Entering Freshmen in Nine Schools and Colleges of the University of Michigan, Fall 1952 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen Test Scores and Grades in Selected Courses, Relationships between 1952 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen Program Interpretation for Students of the test administered 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Grades, Prediction of, Wallace, W.L. undated (Box 2)
  - Graduate Faculty Questionnaire undated (Box 2)
  - LSA Students, evidence regarding the quality of at the University of Michigan (relation between ACE, GPA, and SAT 1960 (Box 2)
  - Nursing Study -- Fall 1953 Freshmen 4 reports (1/29/58, 1/31/58, 2/27/58, 3/27/58), 1958 (Box 2)
  - Norms by Field of Specialization 1952 (Box 2)
  - Orientation Programs (1956), Evaluation of by Incoming Freshmen (Box 2)
  - Test Analysis -- Analysis for Relevance undated (Box 2)
  - SAT -- Selected Comparisons (graphs) LSA, Fall 1955 (Box 2)
  - Scholastic Aptitude Test (SAT) given to Transfer Students, Fall 1956 Norms for percentiles for each student by school (Box 2)
  - SAT, Tables of Intercorrelations (1955 alphabetical by school) 1956 (Box 2)
  - Item Analysis Social Science Vocabulary Test given to freshmen, fall 1947 (Box 2)
  - SQT Study Freshmen Relation of SQT scores to ACE, High School Rank and first-semester grades, Fall 1957. (Box 2)
  - SQT (V&Q) Distribution of scores for Fall 1957 Freshmen (Michigan Residents) also Proposal for SQT preparation, 1956 (Box 2)
  - SQT Study Freshmen, Fall, 1957. Relation of SQT scores to ACE, High School Rank and first-semester grades 1957 (Box 2)
  - SQT, Regents-Alumni Scholarship Applicant Norms for undated (Box 2)
  - "Student Quality, Freshman Grades and the Admissions Problem at the UM" some Facts and Opinions Drawn from 1958 (Box 2)
  - Teaching Seminar Panel on Nature of Student LSA 1957 (Box 2)
  - Test, Achievement in English, Form B (How to interpret 1952 scores) (Box 2)
  - Test, ACE 1949 Edition (How to interpret 1952 scores) (Box 2)
  - Test, Coop English Test C2: Reading Comprehension, Form T (How to interpret 1952 scores) (Box 2)
  - Test, Coop Math Test for Grades 7, 8, and 9, Form X (How to interpret 1952 scores) (Box 2)
  - Test, GED III (How to interpret 1952 Freshmen scores) (Box 2)
  - Test Scores of Graduate Students in Relation to Geographic Location of Undergraduate College, [1948] (Box 2)
  - Test, Math Placement Test, Form B3E (How to interpret 1952 Freshmen scores) (Box 2)
  - Transfer Students, Academic Performance of (Presented at Conference on Higher Education in Michigan 11/19/1957 (Box 2)
  - A Study of Transfer Students in the College of LSA 1948 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program (Info for Proctors) and Clerical 1953-1957 (Box 2)
  - Group Leaders Responsibilities Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Tests 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Objective Tests Non-Engineering 1956 (Box 2)
  - Group Leaders Directions for 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Essay 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Orientation Questionnaires 1956 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation Directions for Questionnaires undated (Box 2)
  - Box 2 (cont.) (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program Questionnaires September 1955 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE College Aptitude Test Variables Q, L, T. Drawn up: May '58 Norm Group: U/M Freshmen, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE 1949 Edition Transfers, University of Michigan, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE College Aptitude Test Variables Q, L, T. Drawn up: May '58 Norm Group: U/M Freshmen, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE Variables QLT Drawn up: May 1959 Norm Group: UM Frosh Fall 1958 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Coop. Reading Comprehension C2:T (V,S,A) -- Drawn up: May, 1958 Norm Group: U/M Freshmen, Fall, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Michigan English Proficiency Test, Parts II & IV. Drawn up: May '58 Norm Group: U/M Freshmen, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for College Qualification Test (CQT-N) -- Drawn up: May, 1958 Norm group: Non-Engineering Freshmen Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for High School Percentile Rank HSPR -- Drawn up: May, 1958 Norm group: U/M Freshmen, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Michigan English Proficiency Test, Parts I & II -- Drawn up: May '58 Norm group: Engineering Freshmen Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for College Qualification Test (CQT) Variable: CQT-Numerical. Drawn up: 9/57 Norm group: LS&A Freshen UM Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE College Aptitude Test -- 49 Ed. Variables: Q, L, T. Drawn up: September 1957 Norm group: Transfers, UM, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Norms for ACE College Aptitude Test Variables: Q, L, T. Drawn up: June '57 Norm group: U/M Freshmen, Fall 1956 (Box 2)
  - Norms: Coop. Eng. Test C2: Reading Comp, Form Z -- Speed First Used: February, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Scholastic Aptitude Test (SAT) Variables: Verbal and Math. N=969. '56 Norm group: Transfer students, UM, Fall 1956 (Box 2)
  - Norms: ACE -- 1949 Ed. (Q, L, and T) First Used: Fall 1956. Norm group: UM., [1956] (Box 2)
  - Norms: Coop. English C2:T (V, S, A) First Used: Fall 1956 Norm group: UM Freshmen, Fall 1955 (Box 2)
  - Norms: Coop. Chemistry Test First Used: Fall 1956 Norm group: Fall 1956 Engineering, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Norms: Michigan English Proficiency Pts III & IV First Used Fall 1956 Norm group UM Freshmen Fall 1955 [1955-56] (Box 2)
  - Norms: High School Percentile Ranks First Used: Fall 1956 Norm group: UM Freshmen, Fall 1955 (Box 2)
  - Norms: Mich. English Proficiency -- Part I First Used: Fall 1956 Norm group: Fall 1955 Engineering, [1955-56] (Box 2)
  - Norms: Math. Placement Test -- Trig. First Used: Fall 1955 Norm group: Fall 1955 Engineering, [1955] (Box 2)
  - Norms (Freshman) for Ohio State University Psychological Exam 1951-1954 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Cooperative College Ability Test (CAT) Form 1A Variable Q Norm Group U/M Freshmen February 1956 (Box 2)
  - Norms for Cooperative Math. Pretest Form X -- Norm Group Engineering Freshmen February 1956 (Box 2)
  - CEEB Tables; Predictor Tables; Regression equations 1962 (Box 2)
  - CEEB French Tests: Results of those given in Spring1961 at UM February 1962 (Box 2)
  - Relation Between CEEB French Test and UM French Placement Exam. Project 254 (Box 2)
  - Chemistry 104 Relationship of CEEB to Grades, Fall Semester 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - CQT and Natural Science Distribution Courses 1957 (Box 2)
  - College Board Scores, HSPR's, and Grades of Resident and Non-Resident Fall 1961, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Cooperative English Test C2T: Reading Comprehension, A Report on 1960 (Box 2)
  - DAT Study No. of Students Entering UM 1955-1958 Who Had Scores in 9th or 10th Grade, October 1962 (Box 2)
  - DAT Michigan Norms 1956-1957 (Box 2)
  - Dallemand's Multiple Regression Program for the 704. Fricke December 1959 (Box 2)
  - Engineering Freshmen -- Fall 1960 Frequencies of ACE and HSPR -- 2 figures (Box 2)
  - College Board Test Requirements for Engineering Students circa 1961-1963 (Box 2)
  - Extension Study Project 223 Milholland 1964 (Box 2)
  - Evaluation and Examinations Division, Function of 1957 (Box 2)
  - Table XX -- CEEB French listening test scores of applicants with 2, 3, 4 years of French & UM students with C or better 1961 (Box 2)
  - French Listening and Reading Tests (CEEB) & Grades in French, Spring 1961 (Box 2)
  - Fig. 2 -- Scores on CEEB French test by students in French 102, 222, etc. Spring 1961 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Language Study The Value of High School Foreign Language 12/23/1960 (Box 2)
  - Foreign Language Study -- The Value of High School Foreign Language for the Study of College Introductory Foreign Language March, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Average Scores of Entering Freshmen, University of Michigan 1955-1964 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Test Scores, Fall 1963 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program -- 1961, 1962 Tables showing results, comparisons, 1961-1962 (Box 2)
  - Table II-percentage of students of 2.00 or better in freshman year at various score levels on CEEB SAT 1962 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program 1960 Tables showing results of testing, 10/21/1960 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen, HSPR and Total ACE of, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen -- Comparisons of Resident and Non-Resident on ACE and HSPR June 1960 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen at the University of Michigan Data on the Quality of 1958 (Box 2)
  - Freshmen -- First Semester with Deficiencies of From 9 to 16 Honor Points 3/16/1961 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program -- Tables Summarizing Results, Fall 1958 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Orientation Test 1958 (Box 2)
  - Freshman Testing Program -- Tables showing results, Fall 1959 (Box 2)
  - Information Sheet B from Committee on Institutional Cooperation, Fall 58-59 Fresh. From R.L. Williams 12/15/1959 (Box 2)
  - Frequency distributions of scores from SAT for 1964 freshmen, 1964 (Box 2)
  - SQT Verbal (Michigan Residents) Freshmen, Fall 1957 (Box 2)
  - Comparison of UM German Placement Test and the CEEB German Reading Test for 31 Freshmen, Fall 1961 (Box 2)
  - Grade-Point Average Computed from HPR and credit hours undated (Box 2)
  - Table 2 -- Regression equations for predicting 1st yr. GPA at UM 1962 (Box 2)
  - Graduate Record Advanced Psychology Exam & Psych. Placement Exam, Results 1958 (Box 2)
  - Intercorrelations of Predictors and GPA Freshmen in LSA 1961 (Box 2)
  - Law School Expectancy Tables for Grades in Law School at UM 12/21/1960 (Box 2)
  - Law School Expectancy Table for Grades, Based on LSAT Scores and Adjusted Undergraduate GPA (9 colleges) 1946-1958 (Box 2)
  - Law School Admissions Study Committee, Study of Criteria used in admission 1960 (Box 2)
  - Entrance Test Scores and High School Ranks of Students Receiving Ds and Es in Distribution Courses, LSA, Project 255, Fall 1963-1964 (Box 2)
  - LSA -- Median GPA HSPR 1955-56 ACE vs 1949 national norms for 4-year Colleges, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Literature, Science and Arts Courses Showing Grade and Quality Level of Students undated (Box 2)
  - Table 3 -- Relation between actual & predicted GPA for women in LSA 1962 (Box 2)
  - Literature, Science and Arts -- Data Taken from the President's Report 1959-1960 (Box 2)
  - LSA, Number of High School Units Taken in Various Subjects by 1934 Freshmen Who Entered the College in September '56, [1956] (Box 2)
  - SAT Scores of Non-Resident LSA Freshmen 1955, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Math 233: Grades of Freshmen, Fall 1962-1963 (Box 2)
  - Mathematical Training of Graduate Students in Eight Areas of Biological, Management, and Social Sciences at the UM 5/26/1961 (Box 2)
  - Michigan High School Graduates 1960 College Enrollment of Top 10 percent, March 1962 (Box 2)
  - Nursing -- 1959 Graduates Who Entered in 1955 SAT Scores and GPAs, October 1962 (Box 2)
  - Orientation Test Results, Fall 1955 Fall 1956 (Box 2)
  - Directions for the OAIS undated (Box 2)
  - Physical Science Distribution Course of Non-Science Majors 1955 Freshmen, October 1960 (Box 2)
  - Prediction of First Year GPA of Freshmen at the University of Michigan February 1960 (Box 2)
  - Psychology Senior Comprehensive Exam Report, Joan Barr June 1959 (Box 2)
  - Psych Graduates -- Follow-up Study 1955-1957 (Box 2)
  - SAT Median Total Scores in Various Concentration Fields in LSA 10/26/1960 (Box 2)
  - SAT and ACE -- Table for Rough Equivalents 1/9/1961 (Box 2)
  - Statistics Courses at the University of Michigan 1961 (Box 2)
  - Test Data -- Use of Test Data by Colleges Milholland August 6, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Teaching Seminar Panel on Nature of Students, LSA 10/14/1957 (Box 2)
  - Academic and Test Performance of Certain University of Michigan Freshmen circa 1955 (Box 2)
  - Testing Programs in the Various Units of the University of Michigan 1/25/1960 (Box 2)
  - Project 40 Transfer Study -- complete Write-up and 9 tables October 1959 (Box 2)
  - Projects of Evaluation and Examinations September 1, 1956-January 1, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Projects of Evaluation and Examination Division 7/1/61 July 1, 1959-June 30, 1961 (Box 2)
  - Projects July 1, 1961-June 15, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Transfer Students graduating in June 1962, 07/06/1962 Project 215, 1962 (Box 2)